<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-27T22:04:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Collegiate Entrepreneurs Organisation, Delhi University</title><subtitle>We Breathe Startups</subtitle><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Interview with Neelam Jain</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Neelam-Jain/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview with Neelam Jain" /><published>2021-06-27T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-06-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Neelam-Jain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Neelam-Jain/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 1:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Many trans people need to leave their homes, they aren’t accepted by their family, (or the society) and their parents even and so why does this issue exist in our society, what is the root cause of this issue?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah. So I tell you, I think this stems from the fact that, um, you know, as a society, we have, uh, gendered everything and we also, our concept of gender is also very skewed. So, we think the only two definitions , only two Genders that the human being can potentially fall into is of a man or a woman, and that is identified by your body. Uh, but your body has nothing to do with how you experience gender, how you feel about yourself, um, and things like that. So I think one of the first and the foremost things is for us, as a society, is to kind of unlearn what is gender really, because if we understood gender, then we wouldn’t make such a big fuss about being trans, and I think the second thing, and it’s more relevant to India itself is how we view the transgender community. Uh, historically you’ve seen transgender. People are living in boarding, begging in sex work because as a society, we want to push them to that extreme
Uh, so in, in that case, I think the parents’ biggest fear and we see this because a lot of them do speak to us and we try and counsel them as well. One of the biggest fears they see is that if my, my son or my daughter transitions, uh, transitions, and if they become a transman or trans woman, uh, in that case, will my child also get involved in begging will they also be forced into sex work and things like that. So I think we need to show parents and others, and like families and society at large, we need to show them a better way of living. We need to show them that, uh, being transgender does not mean that this is what your life is, and this is where you will be. If we can undo some of those things. I think it’ll be much better and I think beyond all of that the biggest thing is, I mean, your child is your child, right? So it does not matter if your child grows up to identify as trans or gender fluid or gay or lesbian : at the end of the day, it’s your child. So why would you ever, uh, and most of them do it because of the fear of the society. So just because we fear what society will think , we cannot stop living our lives. So, yeah, I think that’s, that’s really it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 2:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Do you feel the trans community are marginalized at schools as their peers aren’t sensitized about the issue ?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll give you an example. Um, I think most of us have experienced this. So when I was growing up also, when I was in a school, there was always this one guy in my class who was very feminine, but People would taunt him and ask Why are you not playing with the boys? Why are you not playing sports, et cetera, uh, this person. And, uh, we found out just about two years ago that this person actually grew up to identify as a transgender woman and dropped out of schooling, he , dropped out of school because of all of this. What specifically was the reason we don’t know, but this person just went missing in school at like, I think 11th or something like that. And this is what actually happens with a lot of transgender people and also happens to a lot of people who identify as gay or because they come across so different, right.
That those students next to them itself constantly keep making fun of them. And they eventually ended up leaving education. And then we ask them that, why are you begging, why aren’t you going? And, uh, you know, getting a job or something like that. I think that’s one aspect also that if you’re really focused on, you know, sensitizing and breaking all these norms about gender, sexuality, all of that at a very young age, it would make things better. I also feel that the teachers are involved. I think they’re the first people that we learn everything from, especially at a very young age, um, then being aware then being sensitized, the most important thing, if, because a lot of these kids who get harassed, they get harassed in front of the teachers as well and when we see teachers not taking an action, when we see the school management, not doing anything right now, the government has also launched a scheme, which every school in this, uh, in the country should have a gender neutral toilet, should identify transgender students and create a sepcial avenue for them so that they don’t drop out. How many schools that are actually following it. We really don’t know. So there’s only so much that the government can also do, but the management, uh, you know, the different stakeholders involved at the ground level should be actually be working&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 3:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The government  came up with this law that one needs to have a certificate of a surgery in order to identify as a trans. Now, do you think that is kind of valid and what else the government should do, what else the government can do ?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I think that is slightly misunderstood. Um, because I think someone who was working on the ground,We see the reality very differently. What’s portrayed on the media is very, very different. the media just wants to make an interesting story and that is what the media is doing these days,
Yeah. So the law really says that for anybody to avail a trans ID card, they can do it without the surgery. what do you need the surgery for is if you need your ID card in the name, in the gender identity of a man or a woman
That is a bit conflicting, but what we’re trying to establish, what the government is trying to establish is that there is a difference between people who pre-transition. And then there is a difference between people who post transition. In a utopian world, We wouldn’t want that difference at all, because at the end of the day one should be allowed to experience gender however, they feel like without going through a surgery or not. But right now the system and the processes are not that simplified as yet. I’ll give you an example of this, right? Like you take a trans man. For example, a trans man is someone who was biologically assigned female at birth. This person grows up to identify as a man. Now, what if this person says that I’m okay to give birth? However, I would, my gender that I wanted to affirm should be that of a man as a country.
Are we still in a place where we can understand a man or gender identity of a man giving birth, there are too many complications to things like that. And there are too many layers to it. So what the government essentially is doing is that they’re not ruling out the fact that you can’t get a trans ID card, anybody who self identifies they go through a psychiatric evaluation, which is what is a normal procedure, even in different cities and States at this point because what transgender people experience sometimes it might be on the borderline with experiencing another things as well. So they go to a mandatory psychiatric evaluation, uh, post which they get a certificate saying that, yes, I’m experiencing gender dysphoria or gender incongruence. And then I get my, uh, trans ID. So getting the trans ID is pretty simple, but if I don’t want a trans ID and if I were a trans man, and I said that, I just want my ID card to say that of a man, then I need to go through a surgery. So there are some people in the community who accept this, but there are some who don’t.There are a lot more legal and judicial issues to things like these as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 4:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Does a lot of the ostracization that the trans community faces stems from the fact that they come from very, very backward families ?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Yeah. You know, I used to think more or less the same way that, uh, people who identify as trans and then who come from middle class or upper middle class, or the elite would have it easier versus those from the very grassroots, but it’s actually the other way around. Um, uh, it’s like, uh, I mean,the rich actually worry more about what society thinks uh, it actually works the same way. We see a lot more trans people who come from very affluent families find it extremely difficult, like in the sense they have all the protection and care, but they just cannot, they just cannot come out. They can not experience this in front of them. They cannot tell their relatives about it. Uh, they cannot come out. They cannot, uh, be in a family function, uh, in an express themselves the way that they want to, what we see with the very marginalized.
I mean, the very grassroots level of our society is, uh, I, I think they’ve seen and they’ve exposed a lot more, even if you take, uh, sorry. Even if you take, uh, the whole, uh, system, you know, if, if you see where the government has placed all these camps or all these housing boards where trans people can stay, it is mostly in the slum boards. It is mostly in the areas where the, you know, lower middle class or the people on the poverty lines. And they are so much more exposed to seeing the trans community, et cetera. The acceptance is a lot better. Uh, nevertheless there are challenges on both ends. And I think at the end of the day, it comes down to the person finding the right resource. Like we had this girl who came to us, uh, uh, her name is Ajita and I’ve actually written a blog about her.
She came from this very small village, very close to Salem in Tamil Nadu. And she ran away from her house because her village was really small, like some, one 50 people. And, uh, you know, her coming out and she’s looked at as a man, right in the village, she was already mocked upon so much because she doesn’t have a father. And in the village kept saying that, you know, your father died because you are so feminine, your father died because you wear nail Polish and things like that, so it’s better that you also die. And she was like, I cannot ever come out as a woman in my village. And so she ran away, he ran away, she came to Chennai. She had no idea where to go. She did a Google search and somehow she found us. Um, and from there on her journey started, we gave her some training, uh, placed her in Accenture, where she has been working for over a year now.And then she went back to her village as a transgender woman, uh, you know, carrying a lot of those gifts, et cetera, for her family, for her, her mother, and some of the other people in the, in the village. And nobody spoke a word. Uh, um, I’m not saying that if you become financially independent, everything, all your problems solved. Uh, but I think that’s the, one of the best gateways that we have, uh, possible. And the only thing that we really can do is really spread the awareness at the various levels, whether it’s a Metro cities, dial one, dial to towns, et cetera, that there are organizations that are people that can help. So please just don’t go anywhere else. Like if agita did not find us, she would have probably been into begging and sex work at this point. And she would have thought, okay, this is my life. So, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 5:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How would you feel to see your state, our state pass a non-discrimination law that explicitly recognizes rights of LGBT people?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Yeah, I think that would be, it would be amazing, uh, because the government of a country recognizes trans people and at least protects the rights to some extent, but we’ve completely invalidated LGBT and larger queer community because, um, the government still believes that this is something that is against the order of the nature or whatever. Uh, so I think a statement like that, uh, build a very strong, uh, movement like that passing would be incredible. Um, the rights of our country protects everybody regardless. Uh, but it does not explicitly. And it is important when you are a marginalized community. It should explicitly say that say Dalits cannot be much less on the account of XYZ and similarly for trans people , you know, all of those things. So I think it would be great. Um, the trans bill of rights already has some of those things mentioned. Uh, but again, it caters only to the transgender community., we don’t, you know, completely validate the entire LGBTQ spectrum as yet as a country,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 6:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Has it become easier to approach or companies or to even persuade, the people who are living in these marginalized areas that you can help them? Is it becoming easier or it’s still as difficult ?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has definitely become a lot more easier. Uh, I still remember when we started off in 2017, it was me and another friend of mine who would just go door to door, knock different houses of, uh, you know, these Slums where trans people stay, we’ll go there and we’ll be like, okay, we want to talk to you. This is what we’re doing. And nobody trusted us because the community has been used and abused in so many ways for decades together that for them to see a random person knocking at their doorstep and think that, you know, a good job will be available and their lives will i,prove they just can’t believe it because everybody’s basically use them for photo op or 400 other things. Um, yeah, but it took us some time. Uh, we had to create a lot of positive stories. We had to show work and results to gain the trust of the community.
And right now it has become a lot better. In fact, right now we don’t do any sort of an outreach to identify trans people who want jobs. The community reaches out to us directly, uh, through word of mouth, through our website. Uh, and there are so many people that were getting jobs at this point and the community is so tightly knit, so one person gets the job in an inclusive workspace and they’re actually able to become financially independent. They go and tell another 20 people about it. So that way, yes, I think in terms of corporates, it’s still building up. Um, there is a gap between what the corporates expect in terms of skill and what we’re supposed to provide. So our training arm is something that is becoming a little bit more robust day by day, and we’re trying to solve that problem. Uh, but I think 2021 is, uh, it is a great year to be doing this work compared to the time when we started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 7:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How did,COVID-19 affect your operations? Was it that you really had to work hard to overcome, or you could transition, into the digital mode of working seamlessly?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t seamless at all. Um, because the community that we’re working with is also not so, you know, so digitally equipped as well, like, um, even within the trans community, you have so many layers, right? There are some who are educated, so they can manage, uh, but 40 50% is not that educated. So beyond tik tok or using Facebook, you know, working through all of these teams and coming for training, all of that, wasn’t easy. So remember, I think when COVID hit, uh, we put our residential training programs completely on hold, uh, about 60 people who were supposed to get jobs, uh, during the month of March, April, 2020, we had to stop all of that. Um, and then we told them, you know what, let’s just wait for a few months that should settle down. And then June rent and July rent and August went, and then we were like, nothing’s happening.
And it doesn’t look like it’s going to get better anytime soon. Uh, so what’s really tough. An initial four or five months, all we were doing was only relief work. Uh, so people who were in very difficult situations, we were sending our food materials. We were raising donations and sending money to their families and et cetera. Uh, I think by August, September, we realized that we have to definitely transition. And the move also came from the community saying that, you know what, now we don’t think we even have begging as an option to really survive. We need to do something else in our life. Uh, so a lot of them came forward saying that, uh, you know, we will learn. So we onboarded a bunch of, um, local speaking,, trainers proficient in spoken Hindi, English, kannada, we got them on board. So first couple of days, we didn’t do trainings per se.
We were just engaging them will be like a half an hour of catching up playing activities. And then going from the second week onwards we started doing proper English curriculum training and it actually worked out really well for us. Uh, so right now, like about 70% of all our trainings, everything is happening online, or we just reserved some percent of doing things offline because now things are again getting back to normal. And there are some people who still prefer coming in person and people are also getting the jobs online. So that transitions have also been happening. Uh, and I, I would say this is only because of the resilience of the community that we could act on something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 8:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;This also speaks volumes about the perseverance that you have, your mission has. Uh, and, uh, so you gave this quote by someone that, uh, it’s not important to do well, but it’s more important to do good as well. So we see that you are completely driven by our mission, but in 2017, when you had to make this jump from Goldman Sachs, was it easy or how did you really, you know, (how did you) convince everyone that I knew that( setting up periferry )was something that was needed to be done, your family, uh, people around you.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah. So I’ll be, I’ll be very honest. So I do come from a place of privilege, right? It wasnt like , I had to support my family
or anything like that, my family was self sufficient. So all I needed to do was be financially independent for myself and, uh, ensure that I have a, I mean, I have a career or whatever in case. So I think that itself kind of set things apart because I see a lot of people who have ambition and who have, you know, who have the willingness to do things, but they’re so stuck because they have so many other priorities to take care. So I think that kind of, that was one thing that stood out for me. And the second thing was, I never really announced it to anyone that I was going to do this, because just imagine, or like, if I told my family that I’m going to jump from Goldman to being in the social development sector and then specifically working for trans community, I don’t think this would have ever happened.So, uh, th the way I did this was, I don’t have parents I’m quitting the job. And then because I wanted to join the family business, that’s what I told them initially. And then slowly, little by little as I started getting more comfortable with the work I was doing, I would spend like three, four hours out of my family business every day, just go out on the field, volunteer, understand what’s happening. I started building an MVP or minimum viable product. I started people and getting people jobs even before Periferry was officially set up. So the thing is I had good amount of groundwork done, uh, for me to come up to my parents and say that here, this works, uh, because otherwise it’s not, I mean, I would think I would be unreasonable for them to expect it to, you know, to be completely okay with it.So I, I did some groundwork. I had some proof of concept and when things actually became in the shape of an organization, that’s when I actually announced it to them, not when I was starting off. And for me personally, um, I wanted to be in Goldman mainly for the exposure, uh, and definitely for the salary as well. But I think over a point, it didn’t matter, uh, you know, after working there for a year or so, I realized that I wasn’t, you know, really loving what I was doing. And I wanted to be in a place where I could actually be financially independent. And I knew that being in the development sector can, and social entrepreneurship was growing at this point. So, yeah, I didn’t think too much about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 9:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;One of the most difficult aspects of working with LGBT community is the question of family acceptance. So how important is it to integrate families in the support of LGBT and how can we do it? Get the family of trans community to support them?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we should definitely talk about that. Uh, so I think, like I said, right, uh, the biggest fear that the parents also have, like, it’s two things, right? One is, Oh, what will my child end up doing? If they come out as trans or they come out as gay or, like, will they get accepted? Will they have a job? Where will they be pushed into et cetera? That is one fear. And second is what will people think And all of that, I think the second thing becomes a lot more easier to handle when the first thing is sort of taken care of, uh, which is what we, you know, motivate and, uh, help most of the candidates who reach out to us for jobs. Also, do they tell us I want to completely transition into a man or a woman, et cetera. And we tell them that, listen, just become financially independent into a place that you can take care of yourself.
And, you know, you come across as someone who, who is strong all alone, uh, because when you do that getting because when you are independent, I think finding acceptance from others is a lot more easier. And I think another thing that happens within the community or not is sometimes people don’t accept themselves. And I don’t blame them for that because everybody around you is rejecting and everybody around you is too negative of who you are. The self acceptance becomes such a big problem. Um, I know that people are some of the people who have, you know, made peace with their families were able to do that because they really loved and accepted themselves as who they were. They were really proud of who they were. Uh, and I think when you are proud, when you are bored, when you are happy with who you are, right. Uh, getting people around you to understand that takes time, but it is, it is definitely possible as well. I hope that helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 10:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Yeah, that’s cool. Uh, right. The choices you have made that. So commendable and, uh, what I would now ask is that we all are college students and what can we do, uh, right now, uh, how can we improve ourselves, develop ourselves, do you know, further down the line that even we have the courage to make the choices that you have made to, you know, so what really inspires you to do all this and how have you been able to make these choices?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I think also when I look at my own college days or whatever, I was someone who always explored and by exploring, I don’t mean going to different, different cities and countries and all of that. I didn’t have that sort of a financial bandwidth or whatever, but even within the college campus that I remember that, you know, my friends and everyone will be like, uh we have to get out of the college and go out and party or whatever, or go to a cafe and chill out. But me and a bunch of others would be like, okay, let’s go join NSS. Let’s be a part of the rotaract club. You know, let’s see what’s happening in the drama club, et cetera. And it’s not just because I randomly wanted to explore everything because there was a curiosity.Uh, there was a willingness to learn something new and, and somewhere deep down, I always wanted to challenge myself as well. I couldn’t see myself settling and being okay with okay. . I don’t think I saw my life that way. And I constantly kept challenging myself. I was extremely curious about a lot of things as well. So that really helped me, I feel beyond that, I think at the end of the day, it just comes down to having a lot of courage. Like some of the choices that I made, it could have gone the other way around as well, maybe Periferry as a startup would have never been successful. Maybe we never made it to folks or whatever. Now I’m, I’m happily speaking about it, but I also could have been in a place where all of this wouldn’t have worked and I would have stopped doing it.Maybe I gave up on the way. Uh, but at the end of the day, I still had the courage to make that choice, not knowing whether it will go which way. So I think this is the age that you guys can explore. Our twenties are really the time where you have all the, as much freedom as possible to really explore financially, to explore in terms of, uh, your own skills and meet a lot of people, do things that make you very, very uncomfortable because that’s the only way to really grow. And at the end of the day, have a lot of courage to really pursue what you want. You can do all of this independently without having to depend on your family or your parents for their support.
All right. Thank you so much. It’s really has been a very engaging session and I’m learning quite a lot out of it. Uh, but there’s this one question that we need to ask you that what do you do in your free time? It’s it looks really, you know, from the conversation we are having, it looks quite, uh, different, but this is something I think our readers would also want to know that how are you developing in your free time as well besides doing this? So,
Yeah, it is not a very great answer, but I, I have not had free time as much in the last one to two years. Um, you know, I’m still building a startup that I’m still reading a growing startup and a startup that is gaining a lot of focus. So 90, 99.9% of my time just goes in my startup which is the reason why even on a Sunday, I have to, you know, move all my interviews or whatever, extra sort of out of my day-to-day work. Uh, so the time is packed the little time that I get, I play Ukelele I’ve picked up a new hobby in the last, uh, last six months. So I started learning how to play Ukelele, and I enjoy it because it gives me some peace of mind, you know, apart from my day-to-day, uh, things that keeps happening.
I, uh, I have three cats at home, so they’re my favorite, uh, place to be. Um, I wanted to adopt a few more dogs as well, but my parents were like to survive the culture before you started getting more animals. Um, and, uh, yeah, I spend time with my friends and I love, I love hanging out with my friends. My friends are those, uh, that I’ve known for like very, very long time and, uh, go back to childhood. still connect with them like on weekends or whatever. And I enjoy watching movies in the theater. I think that transports me to another world and, uh, takes me away from everything for a little while the other three or four things that I kind of enjoy doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;QUESTION 11:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Right, So I think we have taken quite a lot of your time. So one last question before you leave, uh, now someone, uh, suppose that there is someone who is also working in an MNC or in the Goldman Sachs somewhere, and he too faces this choice in his life that he can do something, uh, for the betterment of the society as a whole. So what message would you give to him that he should make this leap?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah. See, I don’t want to pass a comment saying you know, make the transition from a MNC and life would be great for you because everyone’s reality is very different. But what I can say is that you, we can be an entrepreneur no matter where we are. Uh, even if you are an employee in Goldman Sachs, you can still be an entrepreneur as well. And that, that is exactly what I did when I was at Goldman. I did not stop at my day job. Uh, I was a part of the LGBT network over there. I spent a lot of time, uh, you know, exploring things, learning from the community and doing a lot of things outside as well. Right. So I had my own identity and I would say, act like an entrepreneur, uh, do not submit yourself into, um, you know, do not submit yourself into whatever’s happening
Own your life, uh, is what I would say. Otherwise, there’ll be other people who will own it for you. Um, so yeah, I think that’s, that’s it. And if you feel like your leap will make things in life, better for you, if that’s the life that you want, because the life of an entrepreneur is not easy, either, there is a lot of things that you have to sacrifice and give up, but if you’re okay with that barter system, you know, and if you’re okay with sacrificing a lot of things, for making impact for having a bigger purpose innovation, then, then you should do it. So to sum it up, you know, act like an entrepreneur, wherever you go, um, make the leap. If that’s the life that you really want at the end of the day, and do not submit into that, this is what my life is, uh, control your life for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">QUESTION 1:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Interview with Gaurav Parchani</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Gaurav-Parchani/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview with Gaurav Parchani" /><published>2021-06-22T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-06-22T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Gaurav-Parchani</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Gaurav-Parchani/">&lt;p&gt;1)	According to you, how hard is it to build an AI/ML based enterprise and what were the major challenges you have tackled in your journey?
The level of difficulty varies significantly depending on the problem statement, industry associated, deployment strategy and market acceptance. It is especially difficult in healthcare domain due to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a)	Lack of constant stream of actionable health data.
b)	Criticality of failures, particularly True Negatives.
c)	Regulations in the healthcare industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2)	Do you think that the healthcare sector will be dominated by AI in the future? If so, what could be the consequences of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Definitely. There’s a global shortage of healthcare professionals and this pandemic amplified the gap. The role that AI will play in this industry will be to provide efficiency of patient management by assisting the HCP’s and thus enabling them to cater to a wider set of patients more efficiently. A collaborative of HCP’s and AI can potentially reduce human errors, triage better and ultimately save lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3)	What are some healthcare sector changes that you think are necessary and would like to see in the upcoming years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulatory framework needs to evolve for accepting not only AI but modern technology solutions. Along with this the inertia of the already strained healthcare industry towards technology will come down. We’ve already seen higher adoption fo tech solutions by doctors and nursing staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4)	Dozee has a price model which the average Indian cannot easily afford. How did you market and position your product so that even the price sensitive Indian population is convinced to buy it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare should be available to anyone and anywhere. We’ve built Dozee keeping this in mind. Innovations in the hardware to reduce cost along with the decision of processing all data on the cloud to distribute cost of computation are the key drivers of making our tech affordable. Moreover we’re moving steadily towards a subscription model for remote patient monitoring to further reduce the cost to the patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5)	You mentioned in an interview that you tried to build a rocket when you were in class 8. I think it’s safe to assume that you were the young Sheldon of your time (I hope you have seen The Big Bang Theory). Do tell us more about that story, it sounds very intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s very kind of you :). I’ve grown up loving puzzles and therefore pursued engineering. The particular story started when I figured out Calcium carbide when put together with water (Please don’t try this at home) generated acetylene which is flammable. Later that day I also figured out that the welding shop in our locality used calcium carbide for welding. I had all the raw ingredients for building the rocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6)	How was your experience working alongside your Business Partner Mudit Dandwate? Were there ever any clashes in opinion? If so, how did you resolve them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mudit is the real man of steel, it’s a privilege everyday to be able to work with him. It would be an understatement to say that we have clashes often of multiple topics. At the end of the day we come to a conclusion and stick to it. It’s easy to do this because both of our motivations are to do whatever’s best for Dozee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7)	In light of the recent pandemic, what all opportunities do you see as a founder of a startup that deals in the healthcare sector?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first word that comes to mind when you put together the phrases pandemic and healthcare founder is responsibility. We enabled multiple government hospitals to set up thousands of step down ICU beds to manage covid patients. We saw this as our responsibility and not an opportunity. Having said that, this is the best time for a healthcare founder as the pandemic has exposed shortcomings in our healthcare systems, both in India and globally. New solutions and startups are built to solve these problems, what better time to build when the problem is evident in your face.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">1) According to you, how hard is it to build an AI/ML based enterprise and what were the major challenges you have tackled in your journey? The level of difficulty varies significantly depending on the problem statement, industry associated, deployment strategy and market acceptance. It is especially difficult in healthcare domain due to the following:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Overvaluation of Startups</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overvaluation of Startups" /><published>2020-03-26T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation/">&lt;p&gt;We all wonder why Uber was valued at $80bn+ (IPO Stage) or Oyo being valued at $10bn, and Zomato coming in at $4bn+. What is common for these investments is overvaluation – a critique of the underlying business models and consequently ridicule for the investors. Another common factor for Uber and Oyo, and potentially Zomato as we move forward is SoftBank – But that’s a topic for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article does not aim to provide a perspective on whether those numbers are justifiable, but aims to provide an oversimplified account of overvaluation of startups from a purely technical perspective. It is derived from the pathbreaking work of Will Gornall (Sauder School of Business, University of British Columbia) and Ilya A. Strebulaev (Graduate School of Business, Stanford University &amp;amp; National Bureau of Economic Research). Before I proceed, I wish to thank the authors for this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Law of One Price&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law of one price is an economics concept which states that any two assets providing identical utility shall have similar prices. Conversely, if one asset is relatively expensive, we shall sell it and buy the cheaper asset provided two assets have identical utility and engage in what is known as arbitrage – the process of earning risk free profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide an example, imagine you own two banana trees. Each tree gives out exactly 10 bananas at the end of every month. These bananas have similar taste, similar length, similar girth and every other considerable characteristic is absolutely identical. Now, one fine day, you need to cut the tree and build a seesaw. Regardless of which tree you cut, you shall get a similar space and build an equally attractive seesaw. Would you as the owner of the two banana trees prefer to cut one over the other? Or would you be equally comfortable with cutting either one of them? Your answer will certainly be the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expand the same concept to any two financial instruments. If two bonds, or two shares of two different companies that are identical in all aspects except name provide you with similar payouts – you shall value them similarly. That is what the law of one price means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: It is important that the reader understand the concept before proceeding any further, as it forms the basis of this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valuation of Startups: From Round A to Round F&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are the founder of a startup, you have 40,000 shares of your company. A Venture Capital fund approaches you and asks for 10,000 new shares – over and above the 40,000 shares of your company – and offers you $10,000 for it. In a typical valuation, that would mean your per share price is $10,000/10,000 – $1 per share. With total share capital base of your company at 40,000 (old) + 10,000 (new) = 50,000 (combined), and a value of $1 per share based on the financing – we arrive at a valuation of $50,000. This valuation of $50,000 is called a post-money valuation – meaning valuation after the money has been invested. Also, if we remove from this $50,000 the $10,000 we have received now, we have $40,000 – value of old shares at current price – this is known as pre-money valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, continue adding 10,000 shares for each new round, the shares must be valued at multiple of 10 i.e. – $10 per share for Series B, $100 per share for Series C, $1,000 per share for series D, $10,000 per share for Series E and finally, $100,000 per share for Series F. At the end of this process, your startup will have a post-money valuation of $100,000 multiplied by 100,000 total shares – implying a total valuation of $10bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our implicit assumption while arriving at the final valuation is that all shares issued in the process are identical – hence the law of one price must apply. Unfortunately, all VC investments are not identical and are accompanied by a host of conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venture Capital Investments: The Typical Investment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As most of you may know, common shareholders come last on the food chain i.e. it is only after paying all expenses of the firm, the interest on borrowings and finally the preference dividend, that the common shareholder gets his or her return. Additionally, depending on jurisdiction, common shareholders may have to bear certain responsibilities if their shareholding crosses a threshold. So, venture capital firms like to opt for what is called a convertible preference share. These shares are preference shares, which are convertible to equity shares, based on certain pre-conditions. This allows venture firms to gain on the upside of a startup firm but limit exposure on the downside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance – Assume that a firm raised $5mn at a pre-money valuation of $45mn. Now, the firm may either shut down, or do fair, or kill it in the marketplace. In the case of outcome 1, we typically look at severe cash crunch and it hardly matters whether you had a preference share or a common share. In the case of outcome 3, the pay-off is huge, such that all investors could not care whether they had a preference share or common share. Where this generally matters is outcome 2, when the firm did okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our case, assume that the firm is eventually acquired by a firm for $50mn. Since this is the same as the post-money valuation, it again wouldn’t matter whether you had held preference shares or common shares. You would receive only your $5mn initial investment back. Now assume the firm is acquired for $60mn. In this case you exercise your option to convert you preference shares into equity shares and receive 10% of the payout i.e. $6mn. A nice 20% profit on your investment. Now assume the firm is acquired for $40mn. In this case, as a preference shareholder you get your $5mn back, whereas if you converted to equity shares – your payout would be $4mn. Hence, a preference shareholder gets additional financial value only when the convertibility of the shares allows such a payout. The investor managed to save 20% of the initial investment in the case of the acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Law of One Price: Revisited&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our preliminary examination reveals that even at a base level of investment, the two shares i.e. the common shares and preference shares issued by companies are not identical. With specific circumstance giving rise to differential cash flow to common and preferred shareholders, we must contend that the Law of One Price does not operate. Even at a base level of convertible preference shares, there is with certainty, at least some overvaluation of startups – since the preferred shareholders get additional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borrowing from our first example in this article – With 40,000 common shares, and 60,000 preference shares, the post-money valuation of $10bn does not hold, since each share cannot be valued at the $100,000 price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do venture capitalists then choose to continue using this method to value their portfolio? Many investors, excepting the likes of the famous Andreseen Horowitx, continue to use this valuation method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epilogue&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next article to this 2 part series, I will attempt to evaluate and explain further complexities in investment structures and how the Law of One Price falls severely in these cases, and the case of why venture investors continue to use this method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gornall, Will and Strebulaev, Ilya A., Squaring Venture Capital Valuations with Reality (Dec 2, 2019). Journal of Financial Economics (JFE), Forthcoming. Available at SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=2955455 or http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2955455&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jarvis, A. (2020). Why do Venture Capitalists want preference shares?. Retrieved 25 February 2020, from https://www.alexanderjarvis.com/why-do-venture-capitalists-want-preference-shares/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">We all wonder why Uber was valued at $80bn+ (IPO Stage) or Oyo being valued at $10bn, and Zomato coming in at $4bn+. What is common for these investments is overvaluation – a critique of the underlying business models and consequently ridicule for the investors. Another common factor for Uber and Oyo, and potentially Zomato as we move forward is SoftBank – But that’s a topic for another day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Clothing, Pay as you slay</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clothing, Pay as you slay" /><published>2020-02-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-02-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/payasyouslay.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Pay as you slay&quot; /&gt;
One of the first hires for McDonald’s, Mr. Harry J Sonneborn told Mr. Ray Kroc – “You’re not in the burger business, you’re in the real estate business.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That one line changed the way McDonald’s did business and turned a hitherto failing business into the world’s largest burger chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, it’s time that the clothing industry changed too. Michelin did it with tyres and it made its way into the HBS Case files. Time to finally get some sales for Peter England?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Porter, the strategy guru talked about Marketing Myopia – referencing the inability of firms to have a holistic view of their offering. The analysis starts with customer’s end use of the product i.e. what value does it provide to the consumer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For clothing, the perceived value is a cover for the body. But as we go up the income pyramid, clothing starts to be value more as a fashion use product – the body cover having been deposited at the base as an order qualifier, fashion value serving as the order winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brands however continue to focus on selling that fashion. As a corporate employee buying 20 shirts for INR 3k per shirt – you spend INR 60k on clothes that become less valuable more due to fashion obsolescence than wear and tear. What if you had to instead pay INR 50k for an annual subscription that would deliver clothes for a week to your home? – ensuring that you don’t need to put in time to purchase, store and maintain clothes. Additionally, this subscription would ensure that you keep getting acces to fresh fashion and never have to worry about that again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could be run with 180 instead of 20 shirts, being circulated and maintained within a group of 9 men with similar body shapes and clothing preferences. That sure must sound difficult, but imagine in an office locale like Gurugram or Noida – thousands of employees flock to the office. The larger the population, the easier it must be to access people with similar preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still doesn’t sound well enough? What if you augmented the service by letting people bid with their credits worth INR 50k for shirts each week? Within the app, if you of course like a shirt too much – you could always just pay the price after having tried it for 2 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value within this model is derived not only from the refreshed fashion but also from a high quality maintenance that the brand will be able to provide. Surely, the clothe manufacturer will be able to lengthen the life of its clothes by taking proper care and eliminate your need to wash, dry and iron the shirts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you still might not concur with this deeper integration. But the best use case for this is present within the tyre industry. Michelin’s pay as you go model uses IoT to deliver higher efficiency per mile driven. The firm provides a service contract embedded with the tyres that enable better maintenance that translates to a long life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This deep integration allowed trucking companies to lower their cost per mile of driving while providing Michelin a healthier bottomline by sales of services that were hitherto considered expensive and futile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are definitely more ways to augment the platform experience. Brands could offer newer fashions and experimental designs and run Kickstarter type campaigns to commercialize fashion design student ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The firms will definitely benefit from lower storefront costs and little to no spoilage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever we may move ahead with as an added service, the core benefit is here to stay. Within the clothing industry, it’s time to Pay as you Slay!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">One of the first hires for McDonald’s, Mr. Harry J Sonneborn told Mr. Ray Kroc – “You’re not in the burger business, you’re in the real estate business.”</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Neobank the bank of the future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/neobank/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neobank the bank of the future" /><published>2020-02-23T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/neobank</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/neobank/">&lt;p&gt;The defining characteristics are two: No brick and mortar branches &amp;amp; no banking licenses. The former of which brings down profitability drastically for traditional banks. Sounds fairly efficient – eliminate the lease rentals and you can give out higher savings interest. People will flock to this bank and soon enough you have a high number of investors – all dying to invest in the bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where’s the catch? Well for starters offering banking services in India requires licenses which are extremely difficult to obtain. Hence, most of these players latch on to existing banks and augment their interest rates with the savings on costs of physical presence. These NeoBanks basically let you use the existing infrastructure at lesser cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that’s where things start to get interesting. Imagine if NeoBanks started making use of all the same infrastructure but offered you more. Better credit, higher interest rate payout and financial analytics – at a cheaper service fee. Could these then be profitable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look closely, and you will see that underneath all of this glamour, we are just looking at a rental play. NeoBanks will “rent” the existing infrastructure provided by the traditional banks and try to work with lower resources – lower manpower and higher automation. If by now you haven’t started seeing this as nothing but a process re-engineering, let’s take it one step further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All NeoBanks offer 4 services that differentiate them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low fee checking accounts
Cheap and easy credit
Financial analytics
Seamless customer service&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a price play – not sustainable as a competitive advantage. The second is very niche – a player like EarlySalary is using similar data services to provide cheap and easy credit, complex financial services cannot be disbursed via these platforms and whence they try and disburse higher credit – we are going to enter a similar situation like the credit market of China. Great pomp with no substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third is extremely valuable. As businesses grow, they are able to afford complex analytics and optimize payout sizes and inventory management. A NeoBank catering to SMEs will definitely help them avail these services for cheap. The last is seamless customer service – frankly $100mn investment to replace the so-called COBOL based infra and rejig the entire system. Does not justify the $1bn poured into the system in the last 2 years as per some reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So underneath all the fancy, what we’re looking at are 2 genuine services which can be provided without all the joomla. The problem with that? Very simple – Valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are case studies of companies with fairly similar vision that struggled to raise $50mn but soon after rebranding the enterprise from financial analytics &amp;amp; artificial intelligence based niche lending to NeoBank, the cap table became a lot more interesting – inviting $100mn pitch ins – firm value at $5bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the global market, these companies are expected to generate some degree of profit because of their command on the same PayPal model. They plan to monetize the 1% service fee charged from retailers. Seems very fair, but assuming a 100% income earned is expensed, you’re still looking at probably 0.25% increase in intrest rate that is sustainable, with 0.75% accounting for charges of financial analytics and the platform fee. In addition, these platforms plan to levy a single service charge. As the number of customers grows, there is a healthy bottomline we can see here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Indian context however, things are not so easy. Indian players with similar structures will face major problems. Much of India’s economy still works offline, and even within that, firms like PayTM have had to provide a 100% direct transfer to bysinesses to break into the market. The Indian small business will certainly take cash to taking payment via digital mode if that implies a 2% cut. This renders all small payments outside the scope of the revenue for the proposed business. It also means that the same SMEs it is trying to target for use of it’s valuable financial analytics platform will not use the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important consideration is the management of money. The Indian banks that are able to transform themselves with similar such digital offerings will most likely not want to partner with NeoBanks in the longer run and the banks that use their licenses as a leverage to get these deals have much higher chances of going bust. Thus the faith that backs the fiat currency would be extremely doubtful. Given that a NeoBank is a probable equity partner and not a customer of the bank, the claims of the consumer of a NeoBank – which does not have to abide to strict Capital Adequacy Norms will fall at a level of negligible recovery in the case of default. Even in the case the books were to show the NeoBank or its customers as a depositor, the claims of small time NeoBank target market will not get desired safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most important concern is the regulator’s approach. RBI has pushed even Payment Banks to have some offline presence and it will view this so-called NeoBank with a similar approach. With an offline presence and severe restrictions on investment (like in the case of payments banks) – there will be none to little money left to be made for a NeoBank and hence makes it an unviable business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution? NeoBanks should work for selling the platform with large contracts for maintenance and equity stake in the bank. Instead of a fixed payout, they can have a variable interest margin payout similar to their target revenue with larger size. This would make the holding firm for all such equity valuable and eliminate all the worries facing these firms. Surely the founder will go home with slightly less money, but when the venture bubble bursts – she will still be afloat.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">The defining characteristics are two: No brick and mortar branches &amp;amp; no banking licenses. The former of which brings down profitability drastically for traditional banks. Sounds fairly efficient – eliminate the lease rentals and you can give out higher savings interest. People will flock to this bank and soon enough you have a high number of investors – all dying to invest in the bank.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How WeChat is Changing Your Internet?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How WeChat is Changing Your Internet?" /><published>2019-10-29T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-10-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat/">&lt;p&gt;in contrast to the internet that we use. The Chinese government has walled the internet in China from the rest of the world with the help of an incredibly complex system of filters and blocks which is also famously called “The Great Firewall”. The Communist Party of China uses The Great Firewall to block any site that it cannot control and that’s the reason why China does not have Facebook, Google, YouTube, Whatsapp or Twitter. This has given birth to a number of Chinese copycats which today have grown into huge companies. For Google there is Baidu, for YouTube, there is Youku and for Twitter, there is Sina Weibo, the list is endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why do we have to care about the Chinese rip-offs? Well, in order to know how the internet will develop, it is very important for us to study them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these rip-offs is WeChat which was developed by Tencent in 2011. Started as a copy of Whatsapp, today around 80% of the Chinese use WeChat (approximately 1 billion people). One may call WeChat the ‘Swiss Knife’ of applications. WeChat does it all! The work of Whatsapp, Facebook, Venmo, UrbanClap, Skype, Uber, Instagram, Amazon, and Tinder. Not only this, but WeChat also has features for which we don’t even have apps, for instance, there are hospitals that have whole appointment booking system, investment services and there are even heat maps that show how crowded a place is like a shopping mall or a tourist site. The amazing thing about WeChat is that all these services are provided by ONE APP! This allows the customer to do everything- from buying a product, posting about it, reviewing it, paying for it, investing the remaining savings and texting about it to their friends all using a single app. This raises the concept of ‘Virality’ which is the tendency of an image, video, or piece of information to be circulated rapidly and widely from one Internet user to another; the quality or fact of being viral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of data generated from WeChat is more than the data generated by Google, Facebook, and Amazon together. This data is gold for the advertisers. But the problem here is that this data is used by the Chinese government for various purposes, often leading to Human Rights violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar problems have also started to arise for us. Under the influenced of WeChat, ironically, western apps have started copying it. For instance, Facebook is coming up with its own cryptocurrency, Whatsapp introduced the feature of video call and Google came up with its payment app. This trend is dangerous for us because such volume and type of personal data in the hands of private businesses can be misused. It may lead to companies and governments tracking each and every movement of the citizens. How this trend of ‘super apps’ turn out will be interesting to watch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">in contrast to the internet that we use. The Chinese government has walled the internet in China from the rest of the world with the help of an incredibly complex system of filters and blocks which is also famously called “The Great Firewall”. The Communist Party of China uses The Great Firewall to block any site that it cannot control and that’s the reason why China does not have Facebook, Google, YouTube, Whatsapp or Twitter. This has given birth to a number of Chinese copycats which today have grown into huge companies. For Google there is Baidu, for YouTube, there is Youku and for Twitter, there is Sina Weibo, the list is endless.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Netflix Probed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/netflix/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Netflix Probed" /><published>2019-06-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-06-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/netflix</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/netflix/">&lt;p&gt;With the growing consumption of online content in the past few years, the concept of physical DVD’s and rentals has phased out. In fact, Netflix has bought the business model of physical DVD rental stores online and it now has 118 million streaming subscribers (not counting the freeloaders) along with a market capitalization of more than $100 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netflix is an online streaming content provider that allows its subscribers to watch movies, TV shows, documentaries, etc. on internet connected devices. The company operates on a subscription-based model where the users select and pay for a monthly subscription plan and this gives them unrestricted access to the online content. The way Netflix operates is, it incurs licensing cost to acquire different content, the production cost for Netflix Originals, marketing costs to stay competitive in the market and this includes the cost of that one month of free Netflix we all get to enjoy guilt-free, along with various other costs that come with running a company. For all these costs the only source of revenue for Netflix is the subscription fee it charges its users. In this case, a big concern for the company should be the number of people who violate the Terms of Use and share their Netflix account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the company is not concerned with nearly 25 million non-paying users, instead of coming up with more restrictive terms of use and putting an end to ‘account sharing’ they introduced family plans at a higher cost so that multiple users can have convenient access to one account. This move wasn’t the company being considerate, this was a way for Netflix to beat us at our own game by getting higher subscription fees from one paying subscriber by offering premium plans for 4 screen viewership. These higher subscription fees only act as a concession for the nearly $2 billion that the company loses out on due to account sharers. While account sharing hurts the pockets of the company which is $12 billion in debt, it acts as a source of marketing for Netflix and helps the brand compete against the aggressive marketing tactics of its competitors like Hulu (Disney, owner of Hulu, recently invested in Synamedia for its anti-sharing algorithm which can hurt the Hulu brand).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netflix can opt to hunt down these account sharers but that would lead to negative publicity for the brand and the company risks losing out on its existing subscriber base. The company has found other ways of cutting costs and staying ahead of its competition. One such way is shelling out money for its original produced content which saves the company licensing costs and now it acts as a differentiating factor for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while we think we are saving our money by mooching off someone’s Netflix account, the company has already lined its pocket with money.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">With the growing consumption of online content in the past few years, the concept of physical DVD’s and rentals has phased out. In fact, Netflix has bought the business model of physical DVD rental stores online and it now has 118 million streaming subscribers (not counting the freeloaders) along with a market capitalization of more than $100 billion.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Amazing Startups that Failed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Failed-Startups/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazing Startups that Failed" /><published>2019-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Failed-Startups</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Failed-Startups/">&lt;p&gt;And why not? After all, stats also show that one of every 2 startup ideas is going to be a big hit within 5 years of its inception, so it might as well be yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in this dynamic environment, it takes a lot to have a successful business, given the level of cut-throat competition that exists today. However, there a lot of factors that affect the success of a startup apart from the competition. This blog talks about some of the mind-boggling fails of some of the best start-ups of their time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pets.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in August 1998, Pets.com was created to sell pet food and accessories via the internet. The premise was that you could ‘buy online and cut out the middleman’ and ‘take advantage of Pets.com’s strong buying power’. Users of the site could browse through different categories; choose products they like and have them conveniently delivered to their home. Think Amazon’s original premise – books – but for pet products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a cute, if awkward, memorable sock puppet puppy as a mascot and a large marketing budget at launch, this site quickly raised $80M in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in late 2000, the start-up crashed after burning through $300 million in about twenty-three months. More than three hundred people were laid off when the site was shut down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be wondering, where did they go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The startup did not invest in market research and validation of the idea. They made a lot of assumptions like people wanted to buy pet supplies online, that they knew how to and that the supplies were compelling enough that people would be willing to wait for a few days instead of just driving immediately to the nearest pet store and getting it themselves. Hence, the startup touted to be a great one, failed because it was before its time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crumbs Bake Shop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crumbs Bake Shop was once the biggest cupcake vendor in the world. Founded in 2003, the company got its kickstart in response to the then-growing trend of interest in cupcakes. Listed as one of Inc.’s fastest-growing companies, the cupcake chain expanded to many different cities, (79 locations in nine states – New York, Illinois, Virginia, Connecticut, New Hampshire, Massachusetts, New Jersey, Rhode Island, California and Washington, D.C.) with dozens of stores. It offered more than 50 varieties of gourmet cupcakes. But this startup failed because it grew too rapidly, sounds weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth was unsustainable for a lot of reasons such as there were too many stores at once with over-optimistic revenue projections and costly leases.  Being a single product business, it ought to have proceeded conservatively but it expanded too rapidly, opening a lot of stores throughout. It expanded heavily in Manhattan, and the rental costs there are not very pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the company had great unit economics when it opened its first few stores, with more than $1 million in sales per store and units that could be opened anywhere, for $300,000. But thinking that new stores would match these projections and taking risky decisions based on them was their next major blunder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also laid too much emphasis on just one product – cupcakes, with 80% of its sales coming in from cupcakes only. It had a very weak foundation as it was a single-commodity business, and the cupcakes were clearly just a phase in the US. I mean who needs 50 different types of cupcakes with exclusive brick and mortar stores for them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the business fell into bankruptcy as soon as the fad of cupcakes passed, in 2014, in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PepperTap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PepperTap was an on-demand hyperlocal grocery delivery start-up based out of Gurgaon. PepperTap began its journey on November 2014 and was founded by Navneet Singh and Milind Sharma. PepperTap was started with a vision to revolutionize grocery shopping: no more queues, no more parking hassles, no more bargaining with sabzi-wallas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They worked on ‘100% Inventory-less’ model, wherein they bought the existing inventory in local stores online to their app. They had a great start, operating in around 31 cities and they were processing, on an average, 20,000 orders per day. They became one of the largest players in India in the online grocery delivery business within a year of operation. They raised a total of $51 million dollars from various investors like Sequoia Capital, SAIF Partners, Snapdeal etc. within 15 months of their operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, everything was sunshine and rainbows, so what led to PepperTap shutting its operations starting 2015? The 100% inventory-less model that it boasted about was the thing that led to their failure. E-Commerce in India has a got an image that it has to be cheaper than physical stores for the people to buy. Therefore, the company burnt all its funding on offering discounts. Since it worked on a zero-inventory model, it meant the company had to pay the MRP to local stores; bear the cost of delivery, technology, operations etc. and still, give the products at a discounted price to its customers. There is no way PepperTap could have achieved profitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For e.g. The start-up raised $51 million in 15 months of operations, i.e., roughly $1,00,000 per day. If they have 20,000 orders per day with the loss of Rs. 200 per order (on discounts and cost of the team), it calculates to a loss of approximately $60,000 per day. The business of raising $1,00,000 per day with a loss of $60,000 per day clearly doesn’t make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fail was a classic case of a business trying to build a beautiful mansion without having fortified its foundation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">And why not? After all, stats also show that one of every 2 startup ideas is going to be a big hit within 5 years of its inception, so it might as well be yours.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Angeltax took away wings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Angel-Tax/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Angeltax took away wings" /><published>2019-05-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Angel-Tax</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Angel-Tax/">&lt;p&gt;Every individual gets
some ideas, but only some can convert them into reality. For
a startup, there are various ways to get funded. One of them
is Angel Funding. There are various investors in the market
who are willing to fund potential startups and the demand for
this kind of funding is relatively high due to the kind of
development these investors provide in the form of advice
and consultations and their contacts in the corporate world
help to escalate business towards growth. These angel
investors also expect a high return on investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is the second biggest hub for startups. According to
NASSCOM, more than 1200 startups came up in 2018,
taking the total number to 7,200 startups. Contradicting the
the vision of promoting entrepreneurship, the startup sector is
now getting pinged under tax scrutiny which is levied on
angel investments and is harmful to its financial health.
Angel tax is the 30.9% income tax payable on the capital
which is raised by startups via an issue of shares at a valuation
where the price is excess of its fair market value. It is the
name given to the provision on share premium and income
from other sources under section 56(2)(vii b) of the
income tax act to prevent money laundering.
The valuation of the startup based on the negotiation
between the company and the investor and has no definite
way. The investors look at the business potential whereas the
officials look at the net asset value of the firm. So, when the
valuation of them is high, the startups have to face a higher tax
burden. This issue started to fuel up when more than 70%
startups started receiving notices to pay tax and to furnish
details on their source of income, bank account statements
and other financial data. Section 68 says that a startup should
be able to prove the genuineness of the source of
investments received and of the source
of such money in the investor’s hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has decided to form small working groups
to assess the much-debated angel tax and has also
liberalized the conditions for startups and investors to shield
them which included a simpler mechanism for startups to
claim exemption from this tax. The certification from the
inter-ministerial board has been done away with. They have
to be recognized with the Department of Industrial Policy and
Promotion (DIPP) to be eligible for a concession for shares
and an application to be sent which will be evaluated within
45 days by the Central Board of Direct Taxes. The
exemption might come up with the condition that these
startups submit an undertaking that they do not launder black
money and are not shell companies. 300-400 startups get funded every year, out of which less than 10% have received
these exemptions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Every individual gets some ideas, but only some can convert them into reality. For a startup, there are various ways to get funded. One of them is Angel Funding. There are various investors in the market who are willing to fund potential startups and the demand for this kind of funding is relatively high due to the kind of development these investors provide in the form of advice and consultations and their contacts in the corporate world help to escalate business towards growth. These angel investors also expect a high return on investment.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unconventional Marketing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/unconventional-marketing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unconventional Marketing" /><published>2019-05-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/unconventional-marketing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/unconventional-marketing/">&lt;p&gt;Marketing and advertising have never been the same since. From advertisements made of poorly convincing scientific facts to marketing campaigns that are alive in the streets, we have indeed come a long way. One such marketing strategy that is the rage today is Guerrilla Marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guerrilla Marketing is all about using unconventional techniques to achieve conventional goals. The word guerrilla here was inspired by guerrilla warfare which is a type of warfare that uses a combination of surprise elements, small &amp;amp; agile teams and efficient arms. Just like the guerrilla warfare, in guerrilla marketing, we can see a lot of similarities like ambushes, raids and surprises.
According to Wikipedia, Guerrilla marketing is an advertisement strategy to promote products or services on the streets or other public places with very little or no money. Since this involves very less money this can be an opportunity for small firms to take on big companies using only creativity, time and energy.
One such famous example is of a horror film produced by students of the University of Central Florida Film Program. The movie, The Blair Witch Project, was shot on a very small budget but it was its marketing technique that turned the sides. The team spread rumours about a fictional character ‘The Blair Witch’. They did this by creating a website to support the existence of the Blair Witch. The used a clickbait type tagline to catch the crowd. ‘In October of 1994, three student filmmakers disappeared in the woods near Burkittsville, Maryland, while shooting a documentary. A year later, their footage was found.’
Soon it became widely popular and also aired on television networks like Bravo. It started getting fans even before it was launched. The creators of the film not only got accepted into crème de la crème of the film schools but also ‘The Blair Witch Project’ grossed $248,639,099 worldwide.
Larger companies have also used similar techniques for their marketing campaigns, using hidden cameras and surprise elements. Coco-Cola has been quite successful in this. Their ‘Happiness Project’ involved a vending machine that delivered more than just cold beverages. They recorded crowd responses to make an advertisement out of it. Spreading moral values and happiness they slowly tried to connect the dots back to sharing a coke. It was advertisements like these that has slowly made marketing more than just explicitly claiming to be the best. The very basis of lifestyle marketing is to slowly convince our subconscious to relate activities to brands.
Redbull created one such image of extreme sports. Bringing together a sugary carbonated drink and life-risking leaps of faith. On 14th October 2012, Red Bull and Austrian extreme athlete Felix Baumgartner set a world record for the highest skydiving jump. With a staggering free fall of 4 minutes, the world stood on its feet to watch it, breaking social media records when they reached over 8 million confirmed concurrent views on YouTube.
These are just some cases where someone smart got his/her products selling without putting a hole in his/her pockets. But today we all know that everybody wants to duck an ad. We all eagerly wait for the skip ad button. Since the days of big billboards and cliché ads are long gone its time that everyone gets on the new boat and starts sailing with the wind.
Good Luck Selling!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Marketing and advertising have never been the same since. From advertisements made of poorly convincing scientific facts to marketing campaigns that are alive in the streets, we have indeed come a long way. One such marketing strategy that is the rage today is Guerrilla Marketing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>