<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-05T15:42:40+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Collegiate Entrepreneurs Organisation, Delhi University</title><subtitle>We Breathe Startups</subtitle><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Overvaluation of Startups</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overvaluation of Startups" /><published>2020-03-26T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation/">&lt;p&gt;We all wonder why Uber was valued at $80bn+ (IPO Stage) or Oyo being valued at $10bn, and Zomato coming in at $4bn+. What is common for these investments is overvaluation – a critique of the underlying business models and consequently ridicule for the investors. Another common factor for Uber and Oyo, and potentially Zomato as we move forward is SoftBank – But that’s a topic for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article does not aim to provide a perspective on whether those numbers are justifiable, but aims to provide an oversimplified account of overvaluation of startups from a purely technical perspective. It is derived from the pathbreaking work of Will Gornall (Sauder School of Business, University of British Columbia) and Ilya A. Strebulaev (Graduate School of Business, Stanford University &amp;amp; National Bureau of Economic Research). Before I proceed, I wish to thank the authors for this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Law of One Price&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law of one price is an economics concept which states that any two assets providing identical utility shall have similar prices. Conversely, if one asset is relatively expensive, we shall sell it and buy the cheaper asset provided two assets have identical utility and engage in what is known as arbitrage – the process of earning risk free profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide an example, imagine you own two banana trees. Each tree gives out exactly 10 bananas at the end of every month. These bananas have similar taste, similar length, similar girth and every other considerable characteristic is absolutely identical. Now, one fine day, you need to cut the tree and build a seesaw. Regardless of which tree you cut, you shall get a similar space and build an equally attractive seesaw. Would you as the owner of the two banana trees prefer to cut one over the other? Or would you be equally comfortable with cutting either one of them? Your answer will certainly be the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expand the same concept to any two financial instruments. If two bonds, or two shares of two different companies that are identical in all aspects except name provide you with similar payouts – you shall value them similarly. That is what the law of one price means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: It is important that the reader understand the concept before proceeding any further, as it forms the basis of this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valuation of Startups: From Round A to Round F&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are the founder of a startup, you have 40,000 shares of your company. A Venture Capital fund approaches you and asks for 10,000 new shares – over and above the 40,000 shares of your company – and offers you $10,000 for it. In a typical valuation, that would mean your per share price is $10,000/10,000 – $1 per share. With total share capital base of your company at 40,000 (old) + 10,000 (new) = 50,000 (combined), and a value of $1 per share based on the financing – we arrive at a valuation of $50,000. This valuation of $50,000 is called a post-money valuation – meaning valuation after the money has been invested. Also, if we remove from this $50,000 the $10,000 we have received now, we have $40,000 – value of old shares at current price – this is known as pre-money valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, continue adding 10,000 shares for each new round, the shares must be valued at multiple of 10 i.e. – $10 per share for Series B, $100 per share for Series C, $1,000 per share for series D, $10,000 per share for Series E and finally, $100,000 per share for Series F. At the end of this process, your startup will have a post-money valuation of $100,000 multiplied by 100,000 total shares – implying a total valuation of $10bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our implicit assumption while arriving at the final valuation is that all shares issued in the process are identical – hence the law of one price must apply. Unfortunately, all VC investments are not identical and are accompanied by a host of conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venture Capital Investments: The Typical Investment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As most of you may know, common shareholders come last on the food chain i.e. it is only after paying all expenses of the firm, the interest on borrowings and finally the preference dividend, that the common shareholder gets his or her return. Additionally, depending on jurisdiction, common shareholders may have to bear certain responsibilities if their shareholding crosses a threshold. So, venture capital firms like to opt for what is called a convertible preference share. These shares are preference shares, which are convertible to equity shares, based on certain pre-conditions. This allows venture firms to gain on the upside of a startup firm but limit exposure on the downside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance – Assume that a firm raised $5mn at a pre-money valuation of $45mn. Now, the firm may either shut down, or do fair, or kill it in the marketplace. In the case of outcome 1, we typically look at severe cash crunch and it hardly matters whether you had a preference share or a common share. In the case of outcome 3, the pay-off is huge, such that all investors could not care whether they had a preference share or common share. Where this generally matters is outcome 2, when the firm did okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our case, assume that the firm is eventually acquired by a firm for $50mn. Since this is the same as the post-money valuation, it again wouldn’t matter whether you had held preference shares or common shares. You would receive only your $5mn initial investment back. Now assume the firm is acquired for $60mn. In this case you exercise your option to convert you preference shares into equity shares and receive 10% of the payout i.e. $6mn. A nice 20% profit on your investment. Now assume the firm is acquired for $40mn. In this case, as a preference shareholder you get your $5mn back, whereas if you converted to equity shares – your payout would be $4mn. Hence, a preference shareholder gets additional financial value only when the convertibility of the shares allows such a payout. The investor managed to save 20% of the initial investment in the case of the acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Law of One Price: Revisited&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our preliminary examination reveals that even at a base level of investment, the two shares i.e. the common shares and preference shares issued by companies are not identical. With specific circumstance giving rise to differential cash flow to common and preferred shareholders, we must contend that the Law of One Price does not operate. Even at a base level of convertible preference shares, there is with certainty, at least some overvaluation of startups – since the preferred shareholders get additional rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borrowing from our first example in this article – With 40,000 common shares, and 60,000 preference shares, the post-money valuation of $10bn does not hold, since each share cannot be valued at the $100,000 price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do venture capitalists then choose to continue using this method to value their portfolio? Many investors, excepting the likes of the famous Andreseen Horowitx, continue to use this valuation method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epilogue&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next article to this 2 part series, I will attempt to evaluate and explain further complexities in investment structures and how the Law of One Price falls severely in these cases, and the case of why venture investors continue to use this method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gornall, Will and Strebulaev, Ilya A., Squaring Venture Capital Valuations with Reality (Dec 2, 2019). Journal of Financial Economics (JFE), Forthcoming. Available at SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=2955455 or http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2955455&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jarvis, A. (2020). Why do Venture Capitalists want preference shares?. Retrieved 25 February 2020, from https://www.alexanderjarvis.com/why-do-venture-capitalists-want-preference-shares/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">We all wonder why Uber was valued at $80bn+ (IPO Stage) or Oyo being valued at $10bn, and Zomato coming in at $4bn+. What is common for these investments is overvaluation – a critique of the underlying business models and consequently ridicule for the investors. Another common factor for Uber and Oyo, and potentially Zomato as we move forward is SoftBank – But that’s a topic for another day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Clothing, Pay as you slay</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clothing, Pay as you slay" /><published>2020-02-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-02-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/payasyouslay.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Pay as you slay&quot; /&gt;
One of the first hires for McDonald’s, Mr. Harry J Sonneborn told Mr. Ray Kroc – “You’re not in the burger business, you’re in the real estate business.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That one line changed the way McDonald’s did business and turned a hitherto failing business into the world’s largest burger chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, it’s time that the clothing industry changed too. Michelin did it with tyres and it made its way into the HBS Case files. Time to finally get some sales for Peter England?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Porter, the strategy guru talked about Marketing Myopia – referencing the inability of firms to have a holistic view of their offering. The analysis starts with customer’s end use of the product i.e. what value does it provide to the consumer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For clothing, the perceived value is a cover for the body. But as we go up the income pyramid, clothing starts to be value more as a fashion use product – the body cover having been deposited at the base as an order qualifier, fashion value serving as the order winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brands however continue to focus on selling that fashion. As a corporate employee buying 20 shirts for INR 3k per shirt – you spend INR 60k on clothes that become less valuable more due to fashion obsolescence than wear and tear. What if you had to instead pay INR 50k for an annual subscription that would deliver clothes for a week to your home? – ensuring that you don’t need to put in time to purchase, store and maintain clothes. Additionally, this subscription would ensure that you keep getting acces to fresh fashion and never have to worry about that again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could be run with 180 instead of 20 shirts, being circulated and maintained within a group of 9 men with similar body shapes and clothing preferences. That sure must sound difficult, but imagine in an office locale like Gurugram or Noida – thousands of employees flock to the office. The larger the population, the easier it must be to access people with similar preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still doesn’t sound well enough? What if you augmented the service by letting people bid with their credits worth INR 50k for shirts each week? Within the app, if you of course like a shirt too much – you could always just pay the price after having tried it for 2 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value within this model is derived not only from the refreshed fashion but also from a high quality maintenance that the brand will be able to provide. Surely, the clothe manufacturer will be able to lengthen the life of its clothes by taking proper care and eliminate your need to wash, dry and iron the shirts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you still might not concur with this deeper integration. But the best use case for this is present within the tyre industry. Michelin’s pay as you go model uses IoT to deliver higher efficiency per mile driven. The firm provides a service contract embedded with the tyres that enable better maintenance that translates to a long life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This deep integration allowed trucking companies to lower their cost per mile of driving while providing Michelin a healthier bottomline by sales of services that were hitherto considered expensive and futile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are definitely more ways to augment the platform experience. Brands could offer newer fashions and experimental designs and run Kickstarter type campaigns to commercialize fashion design student ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The firms will definitely benefit from lower storefront costs and little to no spoilage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever we may move ahead with as an added service, the core benefit is here to stay. Within the clothing industry, it’s time to Pay as you Slay!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">One of the first hires for McDonald’s, Mr. Harry J Sonneborn told Mr. Ray Kroc – “You’re not in the burger business, you’re in the real estate business.”</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/payasyouslay.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Neobank the bank of the future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/neobank/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neobank the bank of the future" /><published>2020-02-23T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/neobank</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/neobank/">&lt;p&gt;The defining characteristics are two: No brick and mortar branches &amp;amp; no banking licenses. The former of which brings down profitability drastically for traditional banks. Sounds fairly efficient – eliminate the lease rentals and you can give out higher savings interest. People will flock to this bank and soon enough you have a high number of investors – all dying to invest in the bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where’s the catch? Well for starters offering banking services in India requires licenses which are extremely difficult to obtain. Hence, most of these players latch on to existing banks and augment their interest rates with the savings on costs of physical presence. These NeoBanks basically let you use the existing infrastructure at lesser cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that’s where things start to get interesting. Imagine if NeoBanks started making use of all the same infrastructure but offered you more. Better credit, higher interest rate payout and financial analytics – at a cheaper service fee. Could these then be profitable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look closely, and you will see that underneath all of this glamour, we are just looking at a rental play. NeoBanks will “rent” the existing infrastructure provided by the traditional banks and try to work with lower resources – lower manpower and higher automation. If by now you haven’t started seeing this as nothing but a process re-engineering, let’s take it one step further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All NeoBanks offer 4 services that differentiate them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low fee checking accounts
Cheap and easy credit
Financial analytics
Seamless customer service&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a price play – not sustainable as a competitive advantage. The second is very niche – a player like EarlySalary is using similar data services to provide cheap and easy credit, complex financial services cannot be disbursed via these platforms and whence they try and disburse higher credit – we are going to enter a similar situation like the credit market of China. Great pomp with no substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third is extremely valuable. As businesses grow, they are able to afford complex analytics and optimize payout sizes and inventory management. A NeoBank catering to SMEs will definitely help them avail these services for cheap. The last is seamless customer service – frankly $100mn investment to replace the so-called COBOL based infra and rejig the entire system. Does not justify the $1bn poured into the system in the last 2 years as per some reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So underneath all the fancy, what we’re looking at are 2 genuine services which can be provided without all the joomla. The problem with that? Very simple – Valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are case studies of companies with fairly similar vision that struggled to raise $50mn but soon after rebranding the enterprise from financial analytics &amp;amp; artificial intelligence based niche lending to NeoBank, the cap table became a lot more interesting – inviting $100mn pitch ins – firm value at $5bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the global market, these companies are expected to generate some degree of profit because of their command on the same PayPal model. They plan to monetize the 1% service fee charged from retailers. Seems very fair, but assuming a 100% income earned is expensed, you’re still looking at probably 0.25% increase in intrest rate that is sustainable, with 0.75% accounting for charges of financial analytics and the platform fee. In addition, these platforms plan to levy a single service charge. As the number of customers grows, there is a healthy bottomline we can see here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Indian context however, things are not so easy. Indian players with similar structures will face major problems. Much of India’s economy still works offline, and even within that, firms like PayTM have had to provide a 100% direct transfer to bysinesses to break into the market. The Indian small business will certainly take cash to taking payment via digital mode if that implies a 2% cut. This renders all small payments outside the scope of the revenue for the proposed business. It also means that the same SMEs it is trying to target for use of it’s valuable financial analytics platform will not use the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important consideration is the management of money. The Indian banks that are able to transform themselves with similar such digital offerings will most likely not want to partner with NeoBanks in the longer run and the banks that use their licenses as a leverage to get these deals have much higher chances of going bust. Thus the faith that backs the fiat currency would be extremely doubtful. Given that a NeoBank is a probable equity partner and not a customer of the bank, the claims of the consumer of a NeoBank – which does not have to abide to strict Capital Adequacy Norms will fall at a level of negligible recovery in the case of default. Even in the case the books were to show the NeoBank or its customers as a depositor, the claims of small time NeoBank target market will not get desired safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most important concern is the regulator’s approach. RBI has pushed even Payment Banks to have some offline presence and it will view this so-called NeoBank with a similar approach. With an offline presence and severe restrictions on investment (like in the case of payments banks) – there will be none to little money left to be made for a NeoBank and hence makes it an unviable business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution? NeoBanks should work for selling the platform with large contracts for maintenance and equity stake in the bank. Instead of a fixed payout, they can have a variable interest margin payout similar to their target revenue with larger size. This would make the holding firm for all such equity valuable and eliminate all the worries facing these firms. Surely the founder will go home with slightly less money, but when the venture bubble bursts – she will still be afloat.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">The defining characteristics are two: No brick and mortar branches &amp;amp; no banking licenses. The former of which brings down profitability drastically for traditional banks. Sounds fairly efficient – eliminate the lease rentals and you can give out higher savings interest. People will flock to this bank and soon enough you have a high number of investors – all dying to invest in the bank.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How WeChat is Changing Your Internet?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How WeChat is Changing Your Internet?" /><published>2019-10-29T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-10-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat/">&lt;p&gt;in contrast to the internet that we use. The Chinese government has walled the internet in China from the rest of the world with the help of an incredibly complex system of filters and blocks which is also famously called “The Great Firewall”. The Communist Party of China uses The Great Firewall to block any site that it cannot control and that’s the reason why China does not have Facebook, Google, YouTube, Whatsapp or Twitter. This has given birth to a number of Chinese copycats which today have grown into huge companies. For Google there is Baidu, for YouTube, there is Youku and for Twitter, there is Sina Weibo, the list is endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why do we have to care about the Chinese rip-offs? Well, in order to know how the internet will develop, it is very important for us to study them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these rip-offs is WeChat which was developed by Tencent in 2011. Started as a copy of Whatsapp, today around 80% of the Chinese use WeChat (approximately 1 billion people). One may call WeChat the ‘Swiss Knife’ of applications. WeChat does it all! The work of Whatsapp, Facebook, Venmo, UrbanClap, Skype, Uber, Instagram, Amazon, and Tinder. Not only this, but WeChat also has features for which we don’t even have apps, for instance, there are hospitals that have whole appointment booking system, investment services and there are even heat maps that show how crowded a place is like a shopping mall or a tourist site. The amazing thing about WeChat is that all these services are provided by ONE APP! This allows the customer to do everything- from buying a product, posting about it, reviewing it, paying for it, investing the remaining savings and texting about it to their friends all using a single app. This raises the concept of ‘Virality’ which is the tendency of an image, video, or piece of information to be circulated rapidly and widely from one Internet user to another; the quality or fact of being viral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of data generated from WeChat is more than the data generated by Google, Facebook, and Amazon together. This data is gold for the advertisers. But the problem here is that this data is used by the Chinese government for various purposes, often leading to Human Rights violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar problems have also started to arise for us. Under the influenced of WeChat, ironically, western apps have started copying it. For instance, Facebook is coming up with its own cryptocurrency, Whatsapp introduced the feature of video call and Google came up with its payment app. This trend is dangerous for us because such volume and type of personal data in the hands of private businesses can be misused. It may lead to companies and governments tracking each and every movement of the citizens. How this trend of ‘super apps’ turn out will be interesting to watch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">in contrast to the internet that we use. The Chinese government has walled the internet in China from the rest of the world with the help of an incredibly complex system of filters and blocks which is also famously called “The Great Firewall”. The Communist Party of China uses The Great Firewall to block any site that it cannot control and that’s the reason why China does not have Facebook, Google, YouTube, Whatsapp or Twitter. This has given birth to a number of Chinese copycats which today have grown into huge companies. For Google there is Baidu, for YouTube, there is Youku and for Twitter, there is Sina Weibo, the list is endless.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/wechat.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Netflix Probed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/netflix/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Netflix Probed" /><published>2019-06-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-06-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/netflix</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/netflix/">&lt;p&gt;With the growing consumption of online content in the past few years, the concept of physical DVD’s and rentals has phased out. In fact, Netflix has bought the business model of physical DVD rental stores online and it now has 118 million streaming subscribers (not counting the freeloaders) along with a market capitalization of more than $100 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netflix is an online streaming content provider that allows its subscribers to watch movies, TV shows, documentaries, etc. on internet connected devices. The company operates on a subscription-based model where the users select and pay for a monthly subscription plan and this gives them unrestricted access to the online content. The way Netflix operates is, it incurs licensing cost to acquire different content, the production cost for Netflix Originals, marketing costs to stay competitive in the market and this includes the cost of that one month of free Netflix we all get to enjoy guilt-free, along with various other costs that come with running a company. For all these costs the only source of revenue for Netflix is the subscription fee it charges its users. In this case, a big concern for the company should be the number of people who violate the Terms of Use and share their Netflix account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the company is not concerned with nearly 25 million non-paying users, instead of coming up with more restrictive terms of use and putting an end to ‘account sharing’ they introduced family plans at a higher cost so that multiple users can have convenient access to one account. This move wasn’t the company being considerate, this was a way for Netflix to beat us at our own game by getting higher subscription fees from one paying subscriber by offering premium plans for 4 screen viewership. These higher subscription fees only act as a concession for the nearly $2 billion that the company loses out on due to account sharers. While account sharing hurts the pockets of the company which is $12 billion in debt, it acts as a source of marketing for Netflix and helps the brand compete against the aggressive marketing tactics of its competitors like Hulu (Disney, owner of Hulu, recently invested in Synamedia for its anti-sharing algorithm which can hurt the Hulu brand).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netflix can opt to hunt down these account sharers but that would lead to negative publicity for the brand and the company risks losing out on its existing subscriber base. The company has found other ways of cutting costs and staying ahead of its competition. One such way is shelling out money for its original produced content which saves the company licensing costs and now it acts as a differentiating factor for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while we think we are saving our money by mooching off someone’s Netflix account, the company has already lined its pocket with money.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">With the growing consumption of online content in the past few years, the concept of physical DVD’s and rentals has phased out. In fact, Netflix has bought the business model of physical DVD rental stores online and it now has 118 million streaming subscribers (not counting the freeloaders) along with a market capitalization of more than $100 billion.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/overvaluation.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Amazing Startups that Failed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Failed-Startups/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazing Startups that Failed" /><published>2019-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Failed-Startups</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Failed-Startups/">&lt;p&gt;And why not? After all, stats also show that one of every 2 startup ideas is going to be a big hit within 5 years of its inception, so it might as well be yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in this dynamic environment, it takes a lot to have a successful business, given the level of cut-throat competition that exists today. However, there a lot of factors that affect the success of a startup apart from the competition. This blog talks about some of the mind-boggling fails of some of the best start-ups of their time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pets.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in August 1998, Pets.com was created to sell pet food and accessories via the internet. The premise was that you could ‘buy online and cut out the middleman’ and ‘take advantage of Pets.com’s strong buying power’. Users of the site could browse through different categories; choose products they like and have them conveniently delivered to their home. Think Amazon’s original premise – books – but for pet products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a cute, if awkward, memorable sock puppet puppy as a mascot and a large marketing budget at launch, this site quickly raised $80M in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in late 2000, the start-up crashed after burning through $300 million in about twenty-three months. More than three hundred people were laid off when the site was shut down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be wondering, where did they go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The startup did not invest in market research and validation of the idea. They made a lot of assumptions like people wanted to buy pet supplies online, that they knew how to and that the supplies were compelling enough that people would be willing to wait for a few days instead of just driving immediately to the nearest pet store and getting it themselves. Hence, the startup touted to be a great one, failed because it was before its time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crumbs Bake Shop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crumbs Bake Shop was once the biggest cupcake vendor in the world. Founded in 2003, the company got its kickstart in response to the then-growing trend of interest in cupcakes. Listed as one of Inc.’s fastest-growing companies, the cupcake chain expanded to many different cities, (79 locations in nine states – New York, Illinois, Virginia, Connecticut, New Hampshire, Massachusetts, New Jersey, Rhode Island, California and Washington, D.C.) with dozens of stores. It offered more than 50 varieties of gourmet cupcakes. But this startup failed because it grew too rapidly, sounds weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth was unsustainable for a lot of reasons such as there were too many stores at once with over-optimistic revenue projections and costly leases.  Being a single product business, it ought to have proceeded conservatively but it expanded too rapidly, opening a lot of stores throughout. It expanded heavily in Manhattan, and the rental costs there are not very pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the company had great unit economics when it opened its first few stores, with more than $1 million in sales per store and units that could be opened anywhere, for $300,000. But thinking that new stores would match these projections and taking risky decisions based on them was their next major blunder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also laid too much emphasis on just one product – cupcakes, with 80% of its sales coming in from cupcakes only. It had a very weak foundation as it was a single-commodity business, and the cupcakes were clearly just a phase in the US. I mean who needs 50 different types of cupcakes with exclusive brick and mortar stores for them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the business fell into bankruptcy as soon as the fad of cupcakes passed, in 2014, in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PepperTap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PepperTap was an on-demand hyperlocal grocery delivery start-up based out of Gurgaon. PepperTap began its journey on November 2014 and was founded by Navneet Singh and Milind Sharma. PepperTap was started with a vision to revolutionize grocery shopping: no more queues, no more parking hassles, no more bargaining with sabzi-wallas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They worked on ‘100% Inventory-less’ model, wherein they bought the existing inventory in local stores online to their app. They had a great start, operating in around 31 cities and they were processing, on an average, 20,000 orders per day. They became one of the largest players in India in the online grocery delivery business within a year of operation. They raised a total of $51 million dollars from various investors like Sequoia Capital, SAIF Partners, Snapdeal etc. within 15 months of their operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, everything was sunshine and rainbows, so what led to PepperTap shutting its operations starting 2015? The 100% inventory-less model that it boasted about was the thing that led to their failure. E-Commerce in India has a got an image that it has to be cheaper than physical stores for the people to buy. Therefore, the company burnt all its funding on offering discounts. Since it worked on a zero-inventory model, it meant the company had to pay the MRP to local stores; bear the cost of delivery, technology, operations etc. and still, give the products at a discounted price to its customers. There is no way PepperTap could have achieved profitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For e.g. The start-up raised $51 million in 15 months of operations, i.e., roughly $1,00,000 per day. If they have 20,000 orders per day with the loss of Rs. 200 per order (on discounts and cost of the team), it calculates to a loss of approximately $60,000 per day. The business of raising $1,00,000 per day with a loss of $60,000 per day clearly doesn’t make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fail was a classic case of a business trying to build a beautiful mansion without having fortified its foundation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">And why not? After all, stats also show that one of every 2 startup ideas is going to be a big hit within 5 years of its inception, so it might as well be yours.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Angeltax took away wings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Angel-Tax/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Angeltax took away wings" /><published>2019-05-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Angel-Tax</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Angel-Tax/">&lt;p&gt;Every individual gets
some ideas, but only some can convert them into reality. For
a startup, there are various ways to get funded. One of them
is Angel Funding. There are various investors in the market
who are willing to fund potential startups and the demand for
this kind of funding is relatively high due to the kind of
development these investors provide in the form of advice
and consultations and their contacts in the corporate world
help to escalate business towards growth. These angel
investors also expect a high return on investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is the second biggest hub for startups. According to
NASSCOM, more than 1200 startups came up in 2018,
taking the total number to 7,200 startups. Contradicting the
the vision of promoting entrepreneurship, the startup sector is
now getting pinged under tax scrutiny which is levied on
angel investments and is harmful to its financial health.
Angel tax is the 30.9% income tax payable on the capital
which is raised by startups via an issue of shares at a valuation
where the price is excess of its fair market value. It is the
name given to the provision on share premium and income
from other sources under section 56(2)(vii b) of the
income tax act to prevent money laundering.
The valuation of the startup based on the negotiation
between the company and the investor and has no definite
way. The investors look at the business potential whereas the
officials look at the net asset value of the firm. So, when the
valuation of them is high, the startups have to face a higher tax
burden. This issue started to fuel up when more than 70%
startups started receiving notices to pay tax and to furnish
details on their source of income, bank account statements
and other financial data. Section 68 says that a startup should
be able to prove the genuineness of the source of
investments received and of the source
of such money in the investor’s hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has decided to form small working groups
to assess the much-debated angel tax and has also
liberalized the conditions for startups and investors to shield
them which included a simpler mechanism for startups to
claim exemption from this tax. The certification from the
inter-ministerial board has been done away with. They have
to be recognized with the Department of Industrial Policy and
Promotion (DIPP) to be eligible for a concession for shares
and an application to be sent which will be evaluated within
45 days by the Central Board of Direct Taxes. The
exemption might come up with the condition that these
startups submit an undertaking that they do not launder black
money and are not shell companies. 300-400 startups get funded every year, out of which less than 10% have received
these exemptions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Every individual gets some ideas, but only some can convert them into reality. For a startup, there are various ways to get funded. One of them is Angel Funding. There are various investors in the market who are willing to fund potential startups and the demand for this kind of funding is relatively high due to the kind of development these investors provide in the form of advice and consultations and their contacts in the corporate world help to escalate business towards growth. These angel investors also expect a high return on investment.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unconventional Marketing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/unconventional-marketing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unconventional Marketing" /><published>2019-05-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/unconventional-marketing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/unconventional-marketing/">&lt;p&gt;Marketing and advertising have never been the same since. From advertisements made of poorly convincing scientific facts to marketing campaigns that are alive in the streets, we have indeed come a long way. One such marketing strategy that is the rage today is Guerrilla Marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guerrilla Marketing is all about using unconventional techniques to achieve conventional goals. The word guerrilla here was inspired by guerrilla warfare which is a type of warfare that uses a combination of surprise elements, small &amp;amp; agile teams and efficient arms. Just like the guerrilla warfare, in guerrilla marketing, we can see a lot of similarities like ambushes, raids and surprises.
According to Wikipedia, Guerrilla marketing is an advertisement strategy to promote products or services on the streets or other public places with very little or no money. Since this involves very less money this can be an opportunity for small firms to take on big companies using only creativity, time and energy.
One such famous example is of a horror film produced by students of the University of Central Florida Film Program. The movie, The Blair Witch Project, was shot on a very small budget but it was its marketing technique that turned the sides. The team spread rumours about a fictional character ‘The Blair Witch’. They did this by creating a website to support the existence of the Blair Witch. The used a clickbait type tagline to catch the crowd. ‘In October of 1994, three student filmmakers disappeared in the woods near Burkittsville, Maryland, while shooting a documentary. A year later, their footage was found.’
Soon it became widely popular and also aired on television networks like Bravo. It started getting fans even before it was launched. The creators of the film not only got accepted into crème de la crème of the film schools but also ‘The Blair Witch Project’ grossed $248,639,099 worldwide.
Larger companies have also used similar techniques for their marketing campaigns, using hidden cameras and surprise elements. Coco-Cola has been quite successful in this. Their ‘Happiness Project’ involved a vending machine that delivered more than just cold beverages. They recorded crowd responses to make an advertisement out of it. Spreading moral values and happiness they slowly tried to connect the dots back to sharing a coke. It was advertisements like these that has slowly made marketing more than just explicitly claiming to be the best. The very basis of lifestyle marketing is to slowly convince our subconscious to relate activities to brands.
Redbull created one such image of extreme sports. Bringing together a sugary carbonated drink and life-risking leaps of faith. On 14th October 2012, Red Bull and Austrian extreme athlete Felix Baumgartner set a world record for the highest skydiving jump. With a staggering free fall of 4 minutes, the world stood on its feet to watch it, breaking social media records when they reached over 8 million confirmed concurrent views on YouTube.
These are just some cases where someone smart got his/her products selling without putting a hole in his/her pockets. But today we all know that everybody wants to duck an ad. We all eagerly wait for the skip ad button. Since the days of big billboards and cliché ads are long gone its time that everyone gets on the new boat and starts sailing with the wind.
Good Luck Selling!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Marketing and advertising have never been the same since. From advertisements made of poorly convincing scientific facts to marketing campaigns that are alive in the streets, we have indeed come a long way. One such marketing strategy that is the rage today is Guerrilla Marketing.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Uber Pricing Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Uber/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uber Pricing Model" /><published>2019-04-22T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-04-22T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Uber</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Uber/">&lt;p&gt;Post midnight, both the riders and the drivers were rushing back home which gave rise to a situation of market disequilibrium. This not only resulted in dissatisfaction amongst customers, but also low reliability. The team then came up with an idea to incentivize the drivers. By offering them extra money, the company was able to increase on-the-road supply of drivers by 70-80%, and more importantly eliminate two-thirds of the unfulfilled requests. Proving that the supply curve was highly elastic and drivers were indeed motivated by price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this model looks like a perfect solution to help customers in need, by motivating drivers and driving supply, this is not the complete picture. After regulations were passed by the Indian government allowing surges only up to a cap and in specific midnight hours, Uber started modifying its dynamic pricing model, as a replacement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New-age startups such as Uber make use of the enormous customer data they have access to. The company works on building a loyal customer base. The algorithm closely analyses the specific locations individual customers are at, at specific hours of the day. Once this relationship is established, incentives such as regular discounting schemes, upgrades are provided as part of the company’s “habit-forming strategy”. The key factor on which the company charges high prices is the “customer willingness” to pay them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uber employs various behavioural scientists, who constantly add weights to different conditions wherein consumers’ propensity to accept higher fare is high. For example, having low battery, travelling to work place induces a sense of urgency. Traveling between a fancy neighbourhood and a city center during peak commuting hours, might cost a premium rate, because the company expects people will pay for it. A ride booked from a corporate card will be cheaper than that booked by a personal card, because an untapped working individual is a potential customer for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analytics team also keeps a close check on the bounce rate to discover if the customers are toggling between different online taxi-providers. To prevent loss of customer base, personalised offers are sent through emails and pop-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keywords also have some role in determining the fare-price. Chances are that the same keywords used multiple times may increase the price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hike in prices is minimal, almost unnoticeable at a glance. However, when you look at the bigger picture, you’ll discover the big game companies like Uber are playing, using our data to their advantage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Post midnight, both the riders and the drivers were rushing back home which gave rise to a situation of market disequilibrium. This not only resulted in dissatisfaction amongst customers, but also low reliability. The team then came up with an idea to incentivize the drivers. By offering them extra money, the company was able to increase on-the-road supply of drivers by 70-80%, and more importantly eliminate two-thirds of the unfulfilled requests. Proving that the supply curve was highly elastic and drivers were indeed motivated by price.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Peek into the Startup Ecosystem</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Start-up-Ecosystem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Peek into the Startup Ecosystem" /><published>2019-04-13T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-04-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Start-up-Ecosystem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Start-up-Ecosystem/">&lt;p&gt;The terms ‘start-up’ and ‘entrepreneurship’ are very common these days and are often used interchangeably with small business. So, let us first understand what a start-up is and how it is different from conventional businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to serial entrepreneur and Silicon Valley legend Steve Blank, a startup is a “temporary organization designed to search for a repeatable and scalable business model.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the startup founder and small business owner are both entrepreneurs; the intent, primary function, and funding of their respective business models are radically different&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A start-up founder intents to change the way ordinary things are done and disrupt the market with a scalable and impactful business model whereas a small business owner intents to be her own boss and secure a place in the market.
Both are bootstrapped initially but if a start-up is successful it receives additional series of funding from Angel Investors, Venture Capitalists, Government and even IPO’s (Initial public Offer). With each funding series the founder’s equity erodes while ownership diversifies, whereas in case of a small business all the funds are invested by the founder and the ownership remains intact with him.
We are Indians, we love following others!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start-ups were blooming all over the world in 90’s and India was soon a part of this budding ecosystem. The software companies brought about the first wave of change in the early 2000’s when the demand for human resource in the IT sector was huge. But at that time, the dream of opening a startup was only for a rare breed of brave entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The change really occurred when the recession hit the global economy in 2008-09. Though the impact on the Indian economy was not drastic, the pressure was still felt by fresh engineering graduates who had a hefty student loan on their shoulders, but no job offers in hand. Now was the time for people to think different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cue came from Silicon Valley, and its startup culture. The idea got in synchronization with the Indian ideology of following one’s own dreams and instantly caught imagination of the young minds pursuing management and technical courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Follow your dreams or work for someone who did”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we can see an entrepreneur as young as 14 and a 45 year-old rising out of his mid life crises. The success of the Silicon Valley Indians – the many millionaires it created – has helped change the Indian mindset towards entrepreneurship. Traditionally a university degree was followed by a job with a large company with whom you stayed till retirement. Only if you were born into a business family were you likely to be an entrepreneur. However, today this model has changed. A university degree may be followed by some practical experience, management training, and a stint at a firm. With this exposure to the world of business we see many Indians now setting up their own ventures which, if unsuccessful, would lead to another venture and hopefully never really retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India stands third in the world, not just in the race of Billionaires!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian entrepreneurial spirit has risen remarkably as India stands second amongst the fastest growing startup countries worldwide – just after the US, reported NASSCOM. Digitization is playing a vital role in this scenario and has provided ample opportunities to develop Indian online market. In fact semi-urban and rural areas are on their way to get more focus than selected few metro cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You go girl!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting fact is that women entrepreneurs have started to become more prominent in the innovation economy. Several women-run start-ups such as LimeRoad, Kaaryah, Zivame, CashKaro, and media tech companies such as YourStory and POPxo have become success inspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government Initiatives&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian government defines a startup as an entity less than seven years young with an annual turnover of less than 250 million rupees and headquartered in India. The ‘Startup India’ initiative, by the country’s Department of Industrial Policy and Promotion helps build a positive, effective ecosystem in the country, turning business ideas into a reality for a flourishing startup environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Central Department of Science and Technology set up India’s first Start-up Village in Kochi as the first PPP model incubator in 2012. In a huge endorsement of Kochi’s Start-up, a similar project was started in Vishakhapatnam. Many universities, under their entrepreneurship policy, provide grace marks and attendance waivers to encourage budding entrepreneurs. Another significant initiative is the setting up of Start-up boot camps in around 100 engineering colleges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting to some stats&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The startups in India saw a 108 per cent growth in total funding from USD 2 billion in 2017 to USD 4.2 billion in 2018. More than 1,200 startups came up in 2018, including eight unicorns, taking the total number to 7,200. The key growth drivers were enterprise software, fintech, healthtech marketplace and edtech. Data analytics, artificial intelligence and IoT startups have been witnessing fastest adoption across industry, NASSCOM reported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time is no far when the term ‘start-up’ as a type of business ownership will be found in the NCERT books.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivansh Mehendiratta</name><email>ceoinfo.du@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">The terms ‘start-up’ and ‘entrepreneurship’ are very common these days and are often used interchangeably with small business. So, let us first understand what a start-up is and how it is different from conventional businesses.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bg.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>